Paula Morin collection: Honest horses, wild horses in the Great Basin, 1999-2001
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Paula Morin collection: Honest horses, wild horses in the Great Basin, 1999-2001
AFC 2013/038
Morin, Paula, 1945-
1459 items; 2 containers; 5 linear inches.
1377 photographs (negatives): film, black & white.
21 photographic prints (giclee prints, handcolored): inkjet, color; various sizes.
2.5 linear inches.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of photographic documentation of wild horse herds in the Nevada Great Basin made by Paula Morin during her work for the Nevada Arts Council, 1999-2001. The photographs were exhibited by the Nevada Arts Council in an exhibiton titled, "Honest Horses: A Portrait of the Mustang in Nevada's Great Basin." The collection includes 21 prints described by the artist as giclee prints made from handpainted black-and-white photographs; one print log, and related publicity materials.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Morin, Paula, 1945- photographer.
Organizations
Nevada Arts Council
Subjects
Horses--Nevada--1990-2000.; Wild horses--Great Basin--Photographs.; Wild horses--Nevada--Photographs.; Wilderness areas--Nevada--Photographs.
Places
Nevada.
Titles
Honest horses, wild horses in the Great Basin
Form/Genre
Inkjet prints.; Manuscripts.; Negatives.; Photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series: Manuscripts and graphic images. The negatives and contact sheets are in a binder, described as Box 2 in the container list.
Acquisition
The Paula Morin collection was purchased by the American Folklife Center in 2013.
Related Material
Related interviews conducted by Paula Morin for the exhibition are in the Nevada Arts Council "Honest Horses" exhibition collection (AFC 2014/019).
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Publication
Morin, Paula. Honest horses: wild horses in the Great Basin (Reno: University of Nevada Press, c2006)
Biographical Notes
Paula Morin is a photographer and oral historian specializing in the photography of wild horses of the Great Basin region of the American West. For more than a decade, she has studied wild horses and conducted interviews about the horses' impact on the ecology and cultural landscape of Nevada.
Born in Hollywood, California, and raised in San Francisco, Morin’s admiration for horses was first inspired by her father, who was raised in Montana. They attended many horse races and polo matches during her childhood. Morin graduated magna cum laude from Southern Oregon University and later pursued post-graduate studies in photographic history and cultural anthropology. She became an independent photographer and field researcher and pursued an interest in the nineteenth-century technique of hand-painted black-and-white photography.
In 1999, Morin received a Rural Community Arts Assistance Grant from the National Endowment for the Arts and the U.S. Forest Service which resulted in the exhibition Honest Horses: A Portrait of the Mustang in Nevada's Great Basin, supported by the Nevada Arts Council.
Scope and Content
Collection of photographic documentation of wild horse herds in the Nevada Great Basin made by Paula Morin during her work for the Nevada Arts Council, 1999-2001.
The manuscript materials include exhibition documentation, a narrative history of wild horses in the Great Basin, background information on the Nevada Touring Initiative, and a teaching module. Also included is a handwritten print log with details about the creation of the giclee prints.
The graphic images include 21 giclee prints, plus more than 1300 black-and-white photographs depicting wild horses in the Great Basin region, as well as other images taken during Morin's fieldwork.
Container List
- Manuscripts
  - Finding aid (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Nevada Touring Initiative: Traveling Exhibit (Box-folder 1/2)
    Administratrive information pertaining to the Nevada Touring Initiative.
  - Promotional Materials (Box-folder 1/3)
    Postcards, flyers, book jackets and schedule of exhibits.
  - Newsletter, September 2001 (Box-folder 1/4)
    Telling the Story of Nevada's Wild Horses State Spotlight: National Assembly of State Arts Agencies
  - Print log: Honest Horses (Box-folder 1/5)
    Detailed processing and image development notes.
- Graphic Images
  - Wild Horses of the Great Basin, 21 giclee prints (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Montgomery Pass and Granite Mountain, June 1999, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Granite Mountain, June 1999, 1 contact sheet and 3 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Augusta Mountains, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 6 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Unidentified location, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Unidentified location, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 6 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Unidentified location, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Unidentified location, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - McCoy, Hole in the Wall, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - McCoy, Hole in the Wall, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - McCoy, Hole in the Wall, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Gary Garvasta, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - McCoy, Hole in the Wall, August 15, 1999, 1 contact sheet and 3 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Reneilles, September 1999, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Stone Cabin and Reneilles, September 1999, 1 contact and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Reneilles, September 1999, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Reneilles and Stone Cabin Valley, September 1999, 1 contact sheet and 6 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Reneilles, September 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Stone Cabin, September 1999, 1 contact sheet and 2 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Reneilles, September 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Reneilles, September 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Reneilles, September 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Seven Troughs, September 1999, 1 contact and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Seven Troughs, September 1999, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Jim Gianola and Follow: Five Horses, January 1, 2000, 1 contact and 6 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Edwards Creek Valley and Alpine Mountains, January 16, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Edwards Creek Valley, January 16, 2000, 1 contact and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Unidentified location, January 16, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Edwards Creek Valley, January 16, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bryan Neubert: Cowboy Poetry, January 27, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bryan Neubert: Cowboy Poetry, January 27, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 6 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Las Vegas, February 3, 2000, 1 contact sheet 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Las Vegas, February 3, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 3 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Las Vegas, February 3, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 6 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Nanny Kent (2/6) and Red Rock Canyon (2/23), March 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Red Rock Canyon, March 23, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Las Vegas: Red Rock Canyon and blue Moon Horses, March 23, 2000, 1 contact and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Red Rock Conversation Area, March 2000, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - IL Ranch, April 12, 2000, 1 contact and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Owhyee, April 12, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Owhyee (4/12) and Newark Valley (5/10), April-May 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Ely-Newark Valley May 9, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Ely-Newark Valley May 10, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Clan Alpine (5/25) and Newark Valley (5/9), January 16, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 5 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bald Mountain (May) Bookkeeper Springs (6/1), May-June 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bookkeeper Springs, June 1, 2000, 1 contact shet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bookkeeper Springs, June 1, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 5 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bookkeeper Springs, June 1, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bookkeeper Springs, June 1, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 6 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bookkeeper Springs: Emergency gather, June 12, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bookkeeper Springs: Emergency gather, June 12, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bookkeeper Springs: Emergency gather, June 12, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 2 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Bookkeeper Springs: Emergency gather, June 12, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 6 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Fish Creek and Owhyee gather, July 6, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 7 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Antelope Valley, July 6, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 2 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Antelope Valley and Fish Creek, July 6, 2000, 1 contact sheet and 4 negative strips (Box-folder 2/1)